Makara Magazine fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Makara Magazine fonds
1975 - 1979
F-116
Q103504031
75 cm of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Makara Magazine
The Pacific Women's Graphic Arts Cooperative, in co-operation with Press Gang Publishers (a feminist press in Vancouver), produced Makara magazine from 1975 to 1978. The magazine was billed as "The Canadian magazine by women for people," and sought to explore alternatives to traditional journal structures and work toward positive social change. Makara is a general interest magazine that reflects a wide range of interests and philosophies, and contains fiction, articles, interviews and dialogue, features, and children's section. The Co-operative, consisting of ten women, controlled the majority of production, with printing and four-colour layout done by Press Gang. Makara stopped publishing after 13 issues because it was not self-supporting; sales and advertising revenues did not cover printing costs or salaries.
published
Full
Revised
Title based on provenance of the fonds.
Fonds consists of records created, received and collected in the process of publishing Makara magazine. Records reflect general operation, correspondence, production, and advertising. Includes correspondence, notes, distribution lists, articles, clippings, surveys, manuscripts, lay-out roughs, illustrations, press releases, contracts, promotional material and notes.
The materials were arranged by the Archivist.
Arts and culture; Communications; Women
The fonds was donated by Margo Dunn to the Simon Fraser University Archives in a series of accessions from 1997 to 1999.
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. No further accruals are expected.
The records of Makara were given to Margo Dunn when the magazine ceased to publish. They were retained in Ms. Dunn's custody until donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
Series descriptions and file lists are available.
- General operational files, 1975 - 1979; F-116-1; 7 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of operational files reflecting the general business activities of Makara magazine. Records reflect the development of editorial policy, distribution, contests, disputes with the post office, indexing, and subject files on International Women's Day. Includes correspondence, notes, distribution lists, articles, clippings, returned surveys, and contest entries.
  - Makara - editorial policy, 1975; F-116-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - Makara - distribution, [ca 1975] - [ca 1979]; F-116-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
  - Makara - fight with Post Office, 1975 - 1979; F-116-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
  - Makara - reviews, 1975 - 1977; F-116-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
  - Makara - indexing, 1976 - 1978; F-116-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
  - Makara - surveys not tabulated, 1976; F-116-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
  - Makara - recycling contest, 1976; F-116-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
  - Makara - International Women's Day, 1978; F-116-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
  - Makara - International Women's Day -- photographs, 1978; F-116-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
  - Makara - ephemera, [ca 1975] - [ca 1979]; F-116-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
- Correspondence, 1975 - 1979; F-116-2; 4 cm of textual records
  Series consists of correspondence created and received by Makara magazine. Includes correspondence with contributors, rejection letters, subscription requests, and general correspondence.
  - Makara - correspondence, 1975 - 1977; F-116-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
  - Makara - correspondence -- advertising, 1975 - 1976; F-116-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
  - Makara - correspondence, 1976; F-116-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
    Restricted in part
  - Makara - correspondence -- rejection letters, 1976; F-116-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
    Restricted in whole
  - Makara - correspondence, 1976 - 1977; F-116-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
    Open with enclosures
    Access review (Sep 26, 2023) – The bulk of the file is open. However, it includes a small number of documents (2) that contain the personal information of identifiable individuals (employment history, medical/psychological history). Restricted documents have been removed (enclosed); the rest of the file is open. Enclosed records may be accessed under a Research Agreement. Consult the reference archivist for more information.
  - Makara - correspondence, 1976 - 1979; F-116-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
    Open, no restrictions
    Access review (Sep 26, 2023) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
- Production records - individual volumes, 1975 - 1978; F-116-3; 38 cm of textual records
  Series consists of production records for individual volumes of Makara. Includes layout roughs, edited manuscripts, illustrations, and complete run of individual issues.
  - Makara - rough layout and manuscripts -- Vol. 1, No. 1, 1975; F-116-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 116-1)
  - Makara - manuscripts -- Vol. 1, No. 2, 1976; F-116-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 116-2)
  - Makara - manuscripts -- Vol. 1, No. 3, 1976; F-116-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 116-2)
  - Makara - manuscripts -- Vol. 1, No. 4, 1976; F-116-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 116-2)
  - Makara - manuscripts -- Vol. 1, No. 6, 1976; F-116-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 116-2)
  - Makara - manuscripts -- Vol. 2, No. 2, 1977; F-116-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 116-2)
  - Makara - manuscripts -- Vol. 2, No. 3, 1977; F-116-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 116-3)
    Access review (Sep 27, 2023) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
  - Makara - manuscripts -- Vol. 2, No. 4, 1977; F-116-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 116-3)
  - Makara - manuscripts -- Vol. 3, No. 1, 1977; F-116-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 116-3)
  - Makara - manuscripts -- Vol. 3, No. 2, 1978; F-116-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 116-3)
  - Makara - manuscripts -- Vol. 3, No. 3, 1978; F-116-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 116-3)
  - Makara - magazine, 1975 - 1978; F-116-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 116-6)
- Production records - general, 1975 - 1978; F-116-4; 17 cm of textual records
  Series consists of production records for which the volume is not known. Includes layout roughs, edited manuscripts, and illustrations.
  - Makara - ideas for articles, 1975 - 1977; F-116-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 116-4)
  - Makara - paste-ups and graphics, 1975 - 1976; F-116-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 116-4)
  - Makara - manuscripts, 1976; F-116-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 116-4)
  - Makara - manuscripts -- Human Rights story, 1976; F-116-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 116-4)
  - Makara - manuscripts -- Claire Culhane prison article, 1976 - 1978; F-116-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 116-4)
    Restricted
    Access review (Sep 27, 2023) – File includes records that contain the personal information of identifiable indviduals (criminal history). File restricted in whole, but may be accessed under a Research Agreement; consult the reference archivist for more information.
  - Makara - manuscripts -- Cam Hubert, 1976 - 1977; F-116-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 116-4)
  - Makara - manuscript -- Charlotte Whitton, 1977; F-116-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 116-4)
  - Makara - manuscript -- Women in the North, 1977; F-116-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 116-4)
  - Makara - manuscript -- Vera B. Williams, [ca 1975] - [ca 1978]; F-116-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 116-4)
  - Makara - manuscript -- Lighthouse typeset, [ca 1975] - [ca 1978]; F-116-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 116-5)
  - Makara - manuscripts, [ca 1975] - [ca 1978]; F-116-4-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 116-5)
  - Makara - manuscripts for future use, [ca 1975] - [ca 1978]; F-116-4-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 116-5)
  - Makara - contributor -- Eve Smith, 1976; F-116-4-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 116-5)
    Pending review
- Advertising, 1975 - 1979; F-116-5; 8 cm of textual records
  Series consists of advertising and promotional material of Makara itself and records of advertising in Makara by other businesses. Includes correspondence, press releases, ad mock-ups, contracts, notes and promotional material.
  Files are open for access in the Archives' reading room.
  - Makara - promotion (media), 1975 - 1976; F-116-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 116-5)
    Open, reading room
  - Makara - advertising 1/2, 1976; F-116-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 116-5)
  - Makara - advertising 2/2, 1976; F-116-5-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 116-5)
  - Makara - advertising -- Vol. 1 No. 4, 1976; F-116-5-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 116-5)
  - Makara - advertising 1/2, 1976 - 1979; F-116-5-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 116-5)
  - Makara - advertising 2/2, 1976 - 1979; F-116-5-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 116-5)
  - Makara - advertising -- promotional ideas, 1976 - 1978; F-116-5-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 116-5)